(R&B MUSIC PLAYS)
♪ You taught me everything
♪ And everything
you've given me
♪ I always keep it inside
♪ You're the driving force
in my life
♪ Yeah-eah-eah-eah
♪ There isn't anything
or anyone that I could be
♪ And it just
wouldn't feel right
♪ If I didn't have you
by my side
♪ Oh, you were there for me
♪ To love and care for me
♪ When skies were gray
♪ Whenever I was down
♪ You were always there
♪ To comfort me
♪ No one else can be
♪ What you have been to me
♪ You will always be
the girl in my life
♪ For all time
♪ Mama
♪ Mama, you know I love you
♪ You know I love you
You know I love you
♪ Mama
You're the queen of my heart
♪ You are
♪ Your love is like tears
from the stars
♪ Mama
I just want you to know
♪ Lovin' you
is like food to my soul
♪ Oh-oh, oh-oh-oh-oh
Yeah, yeah
♪ You are the food
to my soul ♪
AHMAD: My grandma
always said,
family pullin' together
in times of need
will make it strong.
But this here's the story
about my family,
about our family,
about the things
that pulled us together
and the things that
tried to pull us apart.
Let's see.
Where should I begin?
(MUSIC PLAYING)
EMCEE: Let's give it up
for last sister
from the Joseph family
to get married, Bird...
AHMAD: I guess
Aunt Bird's wedding
is as good a place as any.
Everyone who was anyone
was there.
EMCEE: Just the party people
to the dance floor.
If you got more than $5
in your pocket,
let me see you shake it!
We got food! We got music!
We got a party
happening up in here!
There you go, Big Mama.
AHMAD: That's my mom and dad
dancing right there.
They got
two and a half kids...
Me, my sister Kelly,
and whoever that is
in the oven.
And that's Aunt Teri
and Uncle Miles,
like Miles Davis.
They're both lawyers
and got some big-time dough.
I'm talkin'
dollar bills, y'all.
The bride is Big Mama's
youngest, Aunt Ryla,
but we call her Bird
'cause she used to be skinny.
The groom is my new Uncle Lem.
Don't know much about him,
'cept folks always
doggin' him out
'cause he's done time in jail.
Go on, baby.
Go pin it on her.
AHMAD: That's Big Mama there.
Big Mama Joe.
People always said
she never made one enemy
in her whole life,
'cause if she did,
she'd just have 'em over
for some of her green beans,
sweet potato pie,
and southern fried chicken,
and they'd be down
with her after that.
(GIGGLING)
That's my baby.
AHMAD: Reverend Williams.
Ain't even kin,
but he's always got
something to say or eat.
Oh, Mama Joe,
how you doin', baby?
How are you doing?
Oh, you look so good.
Mama Joe, them daughters
are looking good, too.
Oh, especially
that baby Bird.
Baby Bird, I was teasin'
with her a little, Big Mama.
I said, "would you
marry the reverend?"
She said, "Reverend,
if I marry, I got to have
sex every night."
I said, "Well,
put the reverend
down for Tuesday."
♪ Hear, hear
Don't change it up
♪ Something new
♪ Something you thought
underground, huh ♪
Just gonna take my man?
Yeah.
Okay. I see how you do.
AHMAD: Oh, and this is Simuel.
For Bird, he was just
one of the skeletons
in the closet
Big Mama said we all had.
All right...
MAXINE: Uh-uh, look who's here.
What's she doing?
TERI: I don't know.
Get out of my way.
SIMUEL: Heh-heh.
Congratulations.
Would you look
at this girl?
AHMAD: Of course,
by the looks of things,
Lem wasn't doing any better
in the
skeletons-in-the-closet
category.
I don't know,
but I'm going
to go get her.
Come on, Teri.
AHMAD: That was him
with his ex
bumpin' and grindin'
like nobody's business.
AHMAD: Damn, look at that.
Honey?
Hmm?
Who's Big Mama's
favorite grandbaby?
I am.
And what would
my sweet pea
do for Big Mama?
Anything.
Then go find
your Aunt Bird,
tell her to get her
butt in here with
her new husband now.
AHMAD: Being Big Mama's
favorite was no easy job,
especially when it came
to keeping the peace.
But I always did
what she asked,
even if it meant
charging into a bathroom
full of fine,
half-dressed women.
Ahmad, what you want?
Yo, Bird.
What?
Big Mama said
get your Black ass
out here.
Boy, Big Mama ain't told
nobody's Black ass
to get nowhere.
Now you stay
out of grown folks'
business.
I cannot believe
what I just saw.
Me either.
Who invited him?
How did Simuel get here?
I didn't invite him.
Doesn't matter
who invited him.
What were you doing
standing there
letting him feel you up
in your wedding gown?
And now your man
is out there
bumping and grinding with
some Miss Hoochie Mama,
actin' like there wasn't
no wedding less than
ten minutes ago.
Whose man?
Your man, girl. Bumpin'.
Oh, hell, no.
Ain't nobody
about to disrespect me
on my wedding day.
That's what
I'm talking about.
Excuse me, ladies!
And did you see
that dress Miss Thing
had on?
Did you see her behind
in that thing?
Girl, just all up her butt.
You see,
that's what she get,
draggin' somebody in
who ain't got nothin'
and puttin' him off on family.
What you talkin'
about family?
Puttin' him off on me.
I'm the one who paid
for this wedding.
Teri, why you always
got to let everybody know
you pay for everything?
'Cause I do.
Who is that
hoochie-coochie mama
with her fat ass all over
my husband out there
on the dance floor?
MAXINE: I told you.
This is my wedding day!
I'm supposed to be happy.
Shoot. What y'all
talkin' about?
We happy.
This is supposed
to be the happiest day
of your life.
Everybody's happy.
Yeah. We're happy.
But we'd be more happy
if we go out there
and beat that ho' down.
MAN 1: Yeah!
MAN 2: Come on...
MAXINE: There they are.
Let's go get her ass.
MAN: Whoo!
She workin' it on him!
Do it! Do it!
Oh!
Excuse me. Excuse me.
Excuse me...
Yeah. Yeah!
Uh-huh.
Excuse me...
MAN: Shake it.
Shake it. Shake it!
Go on, Big Mama!
AHMAD: You see, right there,
that was just like Big Mama,
always knowin' just what to do
to set things right.
I used to think she and I
had a special connection,
like we shared an inside joke
no one else was in on.
'Course, it wasn't long,
I found out
she had the same connection
with all of us.
Yeah, she was the rock
of the Joseph family,
the one that held us
all together.
Reverend, that sure was a good
sermon today, I tell you...
AHMAD: Part of the reason
we were such a tight family
is 'cause we always had
Sunday dinners at Big Mama's.
That were a tradition that
started down in Mississippi
when the old folks
got together after church
to talk smack and chow down
with some good old soul food.
And Big Mama
kept the tradition going
when she and Granddaddy
moved to Chicago.
Holidays, of course,
were bigger.
More folks, more eats,
more souls,
more soul food.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
People would be rollin' in
from all over,
like Uncle Remus,
who was always hittin'
folks up for $2
'cause he was always broke.
Before Granddaddy died,
he used to own a barber shop,
corner store,
and a laundromat.
Not bad for a Black man
in those days.
'Cause of that,
rumor has it Mama Joe's
got a big stash of loot
hidden away somewhere,
but Mama says
that's nothing but a myth.
(LAUGHING)
We used to always
have eating contests,
which the reverend
would always win.
Then he'd split
after he busted slops
with my mom and aunties.
I can still see my dad now
lookin' like
he wanted to break
Reverend Williams' neck.
Last but not least,
there's Big Mama's brother,
old Uncle Pete,
who ain't left his room
in something like
ten years now.
Go.
AHMAD: Just sits up there
watching his old TV set.
It's kind of a "lights on,
nobody's home" thing.
Uncle Pete, Uncle Pete!
Let's go!
Let's get outta here.
AHMAD: Yeah, those were
the good days, all right,
back before things
took a turn.
KELLY: Mama, Mama!
Uncle Pete's messing with us!
KENNY: I'm tryin'
to do my thing.
Can I do my thing?
Hit me!
Unh! Take that.
Yaah.
BOTH: (SINGING)
♪ I got sunshine...
Ooh, no, baby.
That's too much.
Just put about
four pinches in there.
Now, Mama, how you know
how much to put in there
without using
a measuring cup?
(CHUCKLES)
And why we got to
eat ham hocks anyway?
♪ Well
♪ I guess you'd... ♪
Ham hocks, pig feet,
chitlins...
So we learn how
to make things taste good
by trying things out.
See, soul food cookin'
is about cooking
from the heart.
That's right, Mama.
Psst...
Mm...
What's up, Mama?
TERI: Newlyweds...
If she spent more time
getting her shop together
instead of following
Lem around,
maybe she'd pay me
back that loan.
Teri, you are not hurtin'
'cause you gave Bird money
for that shop.
I loaned her money, Max.
As far as you're concerned,
I'm an ATM...
Automatically Teri's Money.
BIG MAMA:
Oh, you two hush up.
You do this every Sunday.
But Mama,
she started it.
BIG MAMA: Maxine, you go on
and finish those biscuits.
Teri, stop runnin' down
your family.
Pay more attention
to your own man.
You're already
on husband number two.
(GIGGLING)
LEM: Oh, shit, baby.
Ohh...
Oh!
Oh... Oh...
So good... Oh...
Shh... Shh...
Big Mama,
that fried chicken
smells good.
I can't wait to get
some of that.
Oh, baby, don't ever
put anything like this
on the stove.
You could burn
the house down.
Yes, ma'am.
Remember that time
Bird almost burned
the house down?
Big Mama, your arm!
Mama!
Get me some butter, baby.
You don't need butter.
You need ice.
Mama, you ain't been
takin' your insulin?
And I bet you ain't been
to the doctor, either.
Maxine, I told you
I don't need no doctor.
Now, that's nothing that
a little salve, turpentine,
or my herbs won't cure.
Except your diabetes.
(SIGHS)
AHMAD: I didn't know what
diabetes was back then,
but I was sure
about to find out.
REVEREND WILLIAMS:
As we bow our heads
on this special day,
we ask a special prayer
for this table,
a special prayer
for Mother Joe,
who has provided
for the roamin' eye
of the reverend
beautiful breasts
and delicious legs under...
I mean, on the table.
Lord, all I'm askin' is,
bless this bread,
bless this meat,
and bless my stomach,
'cause I's gonna eat.
ALL: Amen!
(INDISTINCT CHATTER
AND LAUGHTER)
Take your time, son.
There you go.
Don't take too much.
Just what you need.
You got to remember, son,
this is for the needy,
not the greedy.
(LAUGHING)
Chicken?
Please.
(CHATTER CONTINUES)
Oh, thank you.
I dreamt of fishes last night.
Ohh... Oh, oh...
REVEREND WILLIAMS: Somebody
been deep-sea fishin'.
Don't look over here.
Don't point over here.
What? You never know.
What's she talking about,
fishes?
Oh, no, it just
means that either
somebody's coming
or somebody in the family
is pregnant.
Or gonna get pregnant.
What you looking
at me for?
MAXINE: Y'all know
she can't be talking about me
'cause this is the last
fish dream right here.
Don't sweep the dust
straight out the door.
If you do, you sweep out
the good fortune.
Whatever that means.
Wasn't that Daddy
that said that?
Daddy was the most
superstitious man
I ever met.
Oh, yeah?
Well, check it out...
I got one, I got one.
If you step on a crack,
you break your mama's back.
(COUGHS)
(CLEARS THROAT)
Did you guys
try my fish cakes?
'Cause I made them this year,
and I'm very proud.
My plate's full.
My plate's full, too.
See, y'all ain't right.
Y'all ain't right,
but that's all right.
I'll take 'em, baby.
That's right.
My boo likes 'em.
That's all that matters.
That's all right, Bird.
You ain't got to worry
about cooking, girl,
'cause you know
you can do some hair.
And we know Miss Teri,
we know she can't
cook nothing.
Ain't that right, Ma?
That's why you always
had me cookin', huh?
TERI: Well,
I wasn't in the kitchen
'cause mama and daddy
kept my head in the books,
and that's why
I'm a successful lawyer...
AHMAD: So as you can see,
Moms and Aunt Teri
don't get along.
Never have, maybe never will.
Big Mama says
she's should've name them
vinegar and oil,
'cause they just don't mix.
It all started
back in the early '80s,
back before I was even born.
The rule was,
if one of the Joseph girls
had a date,
their beau had to bring along
one of the sisters,
you know, like a chaperone.
Back when Teri and my pops
were going out,
Big Mama always had
Moms tag along,
just in case Pops
tried anything.
Hey, all right...
Check it out, doll.
Oh! Mm-hmm.
Mm. Mm. Mm.
Hey...
See, that's how
you got to work it.
See, that's how you got
to learn how to skate.
That's how you
got to do it. Ow!
♪ If you want to step out
with another man ♪
You all right?
AHMAD: Now, I can't
say for sure Mom started it,
but for damn sure
Dad couldn't resist
whatever it was
she was throwing down.
Look at him.
See what I'm saying?
Look out!
Aah!
I told you!
(MOANING)
Kenny...
AHMAD: Mom stole Dad
right out from underneath
Aunt Teri's nose.
And the two haven't
gotten along since.
Teri, Teri...
Get outta the car!
Teri...
Get outta the car now!
Get outta the car
right now! Get out!
Oh, shit!
(YELLING)
Hey, get off her, Teri.
Come on, now...
Come on, now.
Hey, Teri!
Come on, now...
Now, just cut out
all that hoosier jawing.
Y'all do this every Sunday.
Talkin' about I can't cook.
I've been cooking
longer than you've been alive.
Corn bread.
TERI: Corn bread
is my specialty,
from scratch, okay?
(INDISTINCT ARGUING)
Um, Lem...
Why'd you get
thrown in the joint, man?
Kenny, you don't...
KENNY: What?
Look, um...
I ain't gonna lie to y'all.
I made a stupid mistake.
Came here from New York
to help my cousin out, and...
I guess I just
got caught.
Doing?
Kenny, damn.
What?
LEM: Nah, it's all right.
I got caught sellin' a little
somethin'-somethin'...
And he paid his debt
to society,
and it's no different
from Daddy
and his gambling.
See, in life,
we all make some
bad choices.
My husband was gamblin',
and, yeah, he was bad at it.
In fact, we almost
lost this house.
But I worked...
On my hands and knees
cleanin' up after white folks,
takin' in laundry...
See, you do what you
have to do to stay strong,
to save the family,
even if you stumble tryin'.
Now, I'm gonna
tell you something.
One finger pointing the blame
don't make no impact.
But you ball up all them
fingers into a mighty fist,
and you can strike
a mighty blow.
Now, this family
got to be that fist.
Oh, my lord...
Faith...
Come here, baby.
AHMAD: Cousin Faith...
Lord have mercy.
The niece Big Mama took in
after her sister died.
In case you missed the news,
Faith is trouble...
Big-time trouble.
What is she doing here?
AHMAD: Last we heard,
she was strippin' in some
club out in California.
Then some guy
supposedly discovered her
and got her dancing
in rap videos,
though I ain't never seen her
in none of them.
Teri, you can take her,
'cause you know
she ain't staying
with me, Kenny,
and the kids.
BIG MAMA: Ahmad,
kiss your cousin.
AHMAD: Now here she comes.
FAITH: Oh, my God,
you've grown so much.
Hi. Ohh...
BIG MAMA: Rev,
this is my sister's baby.
(CHUCKLING)
Mama Joe, Mama Joe.
Oh...
Aah, ahh...
This is a blessing.
Whoo!
(LAUGHING)
Oh, welcome home.
I think it's time.
KENNY: What?
Your baby?
What's the doctor's number?
(ALL CLAMORING)
What's the name
of the doctor?
I don't know.
BIG MAMA: All right.
I'll get this right now.
Okay. All right.
I got it. I got it.
Just get the door.
Yeah... Okay...
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(BABY CRYING)
(INAUDIBLE)
AHMAD: The birth
of my baby sister,
Faith poppin' in
from out of nowhere,
who could have guessed
things wouldn't just keep
getting better?
And this is where
the problem is.
Mama, it's gonna be
all right, okay?
Here.
Put your sweater on.
I'm not getting
my leg cut off.
Mama, you have to.
There's no blood
circulating to that leg.
You're diabetic.
You haven't
been watching
what you eat.
Nobody's cutting
off my leg.
And that's that.
WOMAN: The last thing
you need, Miss Girl,
is a G-string.
So wait a minute.
You telling me I should
give him some, right?
(CHATTER CONTINUES)
What y'all over there
talking about?
WOMAN: The nasty, darling.
(LAUGHTER)
Now come on, now,
we got clients.
Ohh...
Y'all better slow down.
This is...
Oh, Bird.
I just finished dumping
all the garbage.
Oh, thank you, baby.
Why don't you help me sweep
up some of this hair,
and then call your mama
and see what time
she's gonna pick you up.
All right.
(CHATTERING)
What's up, shorty?
Nice.
Very nice.
I see Teri finally
got up off the dime
and gave you the money
to open up your little shop.
Teri didn't give me anything.
It was an investment.
See, if you had
a-come to me,
I would have
given it to you.
But at what cost?
How much
you willing to sacrifice?
Nothin'.
Mm-mm.
Girl, you are gettin' thick.
All right,
that'll do it.
They'll take care of you
up at the front desk,
and I'll see
you next week.
Let me tell you
something, okay?
I am married now.
Right.
So whatever it is that
you and me had goin' on
before is over with.
Hmm.
And besides,
my husband's name...
Is written
all over my kitty cat.
A weddin' gift.
I know you like
the finer things in life,
and I know your man
can't afford to buy you
shit like that,
him just gettin'
outta jail and all.
When you need me...
Call me.
Hmm?
Later, shorty.
Oh, my God.
Whoo...
(CHUCKLING)
Bring my shorty up right.
Hey, hey...
Hey, baby.
You're gonna love this.
Kenny, what you done
brought up in here?
It's an Apple Performa.
A computer?
It's for the baby.
For the baby.
Uh-huh.
Oh, man, it's got
everything. It's got
a color monitor,
CD-ROM, Internet,
fax, e-mail...
It's got everything.
You don't think
she's a little young
for a computer?
Nah.
What?
You just look beautiful.
Heh. You're silly.
Hold it for one second,
all right?
One second.
See what your daddy got you?
Yeah. See what your daddy got?
Yeah.
(SLOW MUSIC PLAYS)
What you doin', Kenny?
(CHUCKLES)
You are so silly.
What you doing?
Hey... Come here, now.
Mm, with your fine self.
MAXINE: My other baby, huh?
Mm-hmm.
Smellin' all good...
(LAUGHS)
You gonna get
in trouble, now.
What you talkin' 'bout?
You know the doctor said
we gotta wait six weeks.
It's been six weeks.
No, it ain't been
six weeks.
Oh, see, you're wrong.
You know that you're wrong.
(LIGHT KNOCKING ON DOOR)
Did you hear that?
It's the door.
No, it wasn't no door.
MAXINE: Yes.
(KNOCKING)
See who's at the door.
Go see.
Go and see who's at the door.
(KNOCKING CONTINUES)
Hey. What's up, man?
What's up, man?
(SIGHS) I was just, um...
(BABY CRIES)
I mean, uh, I don't
even know why I'm here.
I'm just, uh,
if you're busy,
I'll come back another time.
No, no. Come on in, man.
Come on in.
MAXINE: Who's that, Kenny?
It's Lem.
After you, brother.
How you doin', Lem?
LEM: Hey.
I just need to talk
to you for a minute.
It's, uh,
kind of personal.
It's okay.
See, that's how
we got this one.
You better quit it.
Mm.
So, uh, what's up, man?
I was, um...
I was fired
from my job today.
I lied
on my application.
They ask if you ever
been convicted,
and... I checked no.
See, Kenny, man,
you and Miles, man,
y'all got yourselves
together on the job, too.
I was just hopin' if...
If you knew anybody
or of any
job openings, man.
I'll do anything.
Yo, man, we'll find you
something, all right?
Cool, man. Thanks, man.
(SIGHS)
So now the only thing is,
I gotta find a way to
explain this to Bird, man.
What?
She's high-maintenance,
you know.
I mean, she walks around
the house in Chanel sandals
and shit like that,
and I don't want to
make it seem like
I'm livin' off of her.
No, no, you don't want
to tell her, man.
W-why not?
'Cause you ain't
got a job.
No, you don't wanna
tell a woman...
A Black woman.
And especially a Black woman,
that you ain't got a J-O-B.
It's all right for them
to lie around the house,
but let a man...
A brother.
Especially a brother.
Shit. You could be fixin'
the caps underneath
the kitchen seats or...
Or waterin' plants.
Mm. Washin' the dishes.
Takin' the garbage out.
Here, man.
Let me give you
a little somethin'.
(SCOFFS)
No matter what you do
around the house,
they still will
consider you...
A trifling nigga.
Mm-hmm.
Don't tell her.
AHMAD: Yeah, that was good.
MILES: Ha ha! See that?
Got you with
your own trick, right?
Hey.
AHMAD: Hey, Aunt Teri.
Hey, sweetie.
You staying with us?
Yeah.
Yeah. Kenny and Max
need a little time,
and Kelly's with Bird.
(SIGHS)
I got your favorite tonight.
Yeah, I spent
many hours slaving.
I'm looking
forward to it.
Aunt Teri?
Hmm?
Is Big Mama gonna
get her leg cut off?
You're worried,
aren't you, huh?
Yeah.
I don't know.
Looks like that case
is kicking your butt.
Yeah. I don't know how long
the jury's gonna be out.
And the firm is really
pushing me to be partner.
Well, that's what
you want, right?
To make partner?
Any attorney worth their salt
wants to make partner, Miles.
(DOORBELL BUZZES)
AHMAD: I bet
that's cousin Faith.
I got it.
There's, uh, some money
missing from our savings.
Last week, there was...
I took $5,000 out.
I used it as down payment
for studio time.
Fellas and I are gonna
record a CD.
A CD?
Yeah.
Miles, I thought
you playing with this band
was just a hobby.
Why would you say
something like that?
Because
you're an attorney.
You work for a great firm
with a great reputation.
We could make twice
the amount of money
if you spent
more time on your job
and quit this music crap.
If I wanna take $5,000
of my money out of the bank,
I'll do it.
Only $31,132 are yours.
Tomorrow, we're getting
separate accounts.
Okay, uh...
Just for the books' sake,
next time you take
some money out,
inform me, all right?
Fine.
FAITH: Hi! Hello.
What's up?
Faith, how you doing?
Teri... Hey.
Just wanna say thanks again
for letting me crash here.
Your place
is really fantastic.
So, where do I
put my stuff?
AHMAD: Hard as it was,
Big Mama was finally
convinced to have surgery.
You know your daddy always
said you was the strongest...
And the family gonna need
your strength now.
Now, where's that baby?
Ahmad.
Oh, sweet pea,
I'm gonna be just fine.
Just need you
to be strong.
That's why
I'm doing this for you.
So we gonna be
strong together, okay?
Okay?
AHMAD: After they moved
Big Mama off down the hall,
we all just kind of sat around
on our hands, saying nothing.
I'm gonna use
the restroom, okay?
Stay with Daddy.
I'm sorry.
There was a problem.
(MELANCHOLY MUSIC PLAYING)
DOCTOR: Everything's
gonna be fine...
(SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY)
MAXINE: Ahmad...
Ahmad, baby,
I don't think you
should be in here.
Wait. Come on, baby.
TERI: Where's Kenny?
Ahmad, come on. Ahmad...
AHMAD: The doctor
said Big Mama
suffered a stroke
during surgery
and fell into a coma.
We all kind of knew things
would never be the same,
and all any of us
could feel was bad.
We'll call you.
Look, there's a sign
outside your door
that says you're
willing to train.
Now, I got experience
on the presses,
and I'm a quick learner.
I can do the work.
Like I said, we'll call you.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
(HORN HONKS)
Yo!
I'll check you later.
BOY: All right.
See you, man.
LEM: What's up, man?
Come on get in.
I'll take you home.
Why you all G'd up today, Lem?
(RAP MUSIC PLAYING
ON CAR STEREO)
If I tell you something,
you gotta promise me
you won't tell your mama
or your nosy-ass aunties.
Cool.
I was fired
from my job last week.
I been trying to find
another one,
except things
ain't going so good.
Ah, don't sweat it.
You'll find a gig soon.
You got a lot of confidence
just to be a little shorty.
(CHUCKLES) I get it
from Big Mama, they say.
Big Mama, heh.
Here, throw these
in the glove box for me.
You know I spent some time
in prison, right?
I wouldn't even
have been locked up
if I'd have been smart,
like you seem to be.
You know,
Big Mama's always saying
you gotta love yourself.
Maybe you should try that.
(CHUCKLES) My man.
Well, it's getting late,
and I still have
to grocery shop
for dinner tomorrow.
Okay.
Max, surely,
you don't expect to have
Sunday dinner tomorrow.
Why not?
Jesus, Max, Mama is in a coma.
Yeah I don't know, baby.
Maybe...
No, no, no. I'm not
gonna let her ruin
a 40-year family tradition.
Tradition?
Yes, tradition.
Don't you tell me
about tradition.
I am the oldest one.
I am the responsible one.
I am the one who graduated
from law school.
You're the one
that dropped out
when you were 19.
Something about
your jealousy, Max.
Will you guys stop?
All right, let's just
take a vote.
That's a good idea.
Let's take a vote.
All right, cool.
Let's vote.
Hands in the air for all those
who don't wanna have
Sunday dinner tomorrow.
All right.
Hands in the air
for all those who wanna
be sitting in front of
some chitlins,
black-eyed peas, greens,
some fried chicken,
macaroni and cheese,
and egg pie.
I won't let you
disrespect my mama
like she's already dead.
Your mama?
Mm-hmm.
You know, Teri, you get
on my fuckin' nerves with...
Will you lower your voice?
Don't nobody care
if you graduated!
That don't make you
better than nobody!
(VOICES OVERLAPPING)
Keep your voice down.
You guys, stop it.
DOCTOR: I'm sorry.
I'm gonna have to ask
all of you to leave now.
Mrs. Joseph needs quiet.
I'm sorry.
MAXINE: I'm outta here.
Come on, Kenny!
DOCTOR: I'm sorry.
MAXINE: Whatever.
I'm outta here.
Come on, let's go.
We're outta here.
KENNY: Max, that wasn't
even necessary.
That's all right.
I'm tired of her.
She's always
got something to say.
Where's my coat? Come on.
Maybe we should
think about this.
No.
AHMAD: Grandma's illness
was taking its toll
on the family.
Nobody knew where
to throw the blame,
except at each other.
Aunt Teri and Moms especially.
Because of them,
hardly no one
was speaking anymore.
(INAUDIBLE)
Poor Aunt Bird.
She tried her best to pull off
that Sunday's dinner
all by herself.
Because of Teri
and Mom's fight,
no one showed up.
It was the first time
in 40 years
our Sunday tradition
was broken.
Let's just eat.
Here you go.
(TELEVISION PLAYING)
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
Uncle Pete?
Dinner.
(SIGHS)
(VITALS MONITOR BEEPING)
I know you think
I been avoiding you.
It's just that every time
I come by to see you,
there's always people around
doing stuff to you
or arguing around you.
Anyway, I know
you're wondering how
everyone else is doing.
Not good.
We didn't have
a Sunday dinner yesterday.
Aunt Bird said
nobody showed up.
After church, Mom didn't
feel like cooking at home,
so Daddy brought home
some Mickey D's.
We were all
on the toilet all night.
(CHUCKLES)
We need you, Big Mama.
Yeah, I was
thinking that, too.
Maybe when you
get out of here,
I could help you
turn the ground over.
As you called it,
put some fertilizer down.
Yeah, I'll help you.
Come dance with me.
What?
Come on.
Miles...
Come on. Come on.
Dance?
Dance.
I don't wanna dance.
Oh, come on.
Miles...
You know, Mama
is not doing well at all.
Yeah, I know, and come
dance with me
and get your mind off it.
Um, I also can't go
to see you perform tonight.
That's what
you said last week
and the week before.
I'd really like you to come...
You know I'm
swamped with work.
(SIGHS) Okay.
Well, just so you know...
I'm thinking about pursuing
my music full time.
Miles...
That's a mistake.
It's what I wanna do.
You find a job yet?
Nope.
But I have an audition
coming up.
I'm just not into
the straight job thing.
"Straight job thing"?
Look, I didn't plan
on staying here.
I thought I was gonna be
at Mama Joe's.
If you want me to leave,
I'll leave.
Why'd you come
back here, Faith?
What are you gonna do
this time?
Run up Mama's credit? Hmm?
Or, um, make her
co-sign on a car,
and then you leave her
with the note.
Or better yet,
why don't you get
arrested again,
and let Mama
put up the house
to post your bail.
I've changed.
You've changed?
Don't you try to start
any shit this time.
You hear me?
♪ Oh, ahh
♪ Girl, I care about you
♪ I'm there for you
♪ So why don't you
care for me?
♪ Like I care about you
♪ Oh, girl, I care about you
♪ I'm there for you
♪ So why don't you
care for me?
♪ Like I care about you
♪ I spend, like
All of my days, baby
♪ Tryin' to suss out just
how things got this way
♪ I thought
that we were in love
♪ But I swear right now
I don't know what you want
♪ I make sure that
I give you quality time
♪ But lately I feel
you're not home by design
♪ But still I'm gonna try
♪ To give you the love
of my life
♪ In hopes that you
♪ That you will open up
your eyes, baby
♪ Girl, I care about you
♪ Yeah
♪ I'm there for you
♪ So why don't you
care for me?
♪ Like I care about you
♪ Sometimes
♪ Sometimes I'm not
♪ I'm not sure that
♪ I'm all you got
♪ That I'm all you got
♪ Sometimes
♪ Sometimes I'm not sure
you love me or not, baby
♪ There's one thing
that I'm certain of
♪ Girl, I care for you
♪ And the one thing
that I want is that you
♪ Care for me, too
♪ Girl, I care about you
♪ I'm there for you
♪ So why don't you
care for me?
♪ Would you care for me, baby?
♪ Like I care about you
♪ Baby, baby, baby, baby
Baby, baby, baby
♪ Oh, girl
♪ Yeah, oh, yeah
♪ Ohh, ooh
♪ I care for you ♪
(APPLAUSE)
That was the bomb.
I'm serious, cousin.
You was jammin'.
Man, I didn't know
you could play like that.
You're good.
Thanks, but it's not
just about me.
I mean, we're a group,
you know?
Besides, the way
those guys sing, they...
They just make
my stuff come alive.
But you're the mastermind.
You put all this together.
This is your shit.
The group's
called "Milestone."
It ain't called "them."
(CHUCKLES) We were
thinking about that name.
So, you really wanna
pursue your music
full time, huh?
I heard you and Teri talking.
Your man's looking over here.
He's looking a little jealous.
(LAUGHS)
Family comes first.
Besides, I gotta get my career
together before I can even
think about a man.
See, I got goals, okay?
Okay.
(LAUGHING)
All right.
Promise not to laugh.
Jesus, see? Right there.
I promise. I promise.
Okay. Fine.
I wanna dance.
No, no, no.
I mean really dance.
You know,
do Broadway musicals,
choreograph the Oscars.
I've spent the last
few years of my life
trying to figure out
what makes me happy,
and I learned that
the only thing
that keeps me sane
is dancing.
So I'm gonna put every inch
of my energy into it,
so help me, Jesus.
Praise the lord.
And plus...
It just...
It just feels so damn good.
You know what I mean?
It's like that with you
and your music, right?
You want another drink?
Mm-hmm.
Mm-hmm?
Okay. Sly...
Let's get another one
over here, all right?
SLY: All right.
(ROMANTIC SONG PLAYING)
Ooh... Listen.
Oh, that's my jam.
Oh, come
and dance with me.
Uh-uh.
I'm on my break.
Come on.
What the hell.
It's stupid, honey.
But she really thought
her hair was doing something.
It was to' up,
to' back and over. Hello.
So you cooked all this food
and none of your people
showed up?
And you know
I wasn't having it.
Oh I know you wanted
to embarrass somebody.
Ooh, well,
we can help you get
rid of some of this.
Now I know why none of
her people showed up.
Miss Thing can't cook.
You can't cook, darling.
What is this...
(THUDDING)
What was that?
Shh.
Why you always gotta
push me, honey?
(INDISTINCT WHISPERING)
Aah!
Wait! Wait! Stop! Stop! Stop!
What you hit me for?
No, him!
Stop!
What?
What the hell y'all doing?
Hoo.
Ohh...
Get in the bathroom.
Oh, my God.
Did you see that thing?
What are you doing home
in the middle
of the afternoon?
I got fired from my job.
What do you mean
you got fired?
What, you can't
take workin' a nine-to-five?
You got in trouble again?
No, no. I got fired
'cause I lied
on my application
about being convicted.
And you felt like you
couldn't tell me that?
I wanted to tell you...
But Kenny thought it'd be
in your best interests
if you just didn't know.
Kenny? You gonna
listen to Kenny?
Well, what about us?
It's not about us!
It's about this stupid-ass,
bullshit system.
They lock you up
and expect you
to do something better
with your life,
but when you get out,
there ain't nothing better
'cause the crackers
that got everything
don't give you
a second chance.
You know what?
That white man shit is old,
and I'm sick and tired
of niggas using that shit
as an excuse.
Hey, hey. I'm the one
who's been on six interviews.
Six!
They won't hire me.
So, what you know about
being a Black man, anyway?
You're right. I don't know
shit about being a Black man!
(CLICKS TONGUE)
I'm sorry.
Look, boo, the shop is
doing really well right now.
I'll just...
I'll just pay for our bills.
And there's a lot of people
that come through there.
I'll see if anybody can
hook you up with a job.
Bird...
I don't need your help.
I can find my own damn job.
Okay.
And stop looking
at my dick!
(ARGUING INDISTINCTLY)
MAN: Pay in full!
All right? Full!
Pay in full!
Money up front!
All right?
You can't take the money
right before I go in!
This is so wrong!
Hey, Miles.
You all right?
I'm five minutes away
from the most important
audition in my life,
and this fool is trying
to screw me over.
Look. It's about principles.
Business is business.
You know something?
I'm gonna fuck you up,
Dread Man!
Oh, Miles,
you can help me.
Look, they got a piano
up in the audition room.
Look, all you gotta do...
Faith, I don't...
Just play anything,
and I'll just dance to it.
Come on, cuz, please?
This is really
important to me.
I'll owe you.
(SIGHS)
WOMAN: Ready when you are.
(PLAYS SLOW BALLAD INTRO)
(PLAYS MODERATE TEMPO)
Okay, Keesha, we have
you down at 10:00
with Stefan.
Thanks. Bye.
I knew you'd call.
Simuel. Let me take
your briefcase, baby.
Come on over here.
Here we go.
I'm so glad
you could make it.
There's something
I wanna talk to you about.
Is that right?
HAROME: Ooh! Uh-uh!
Yeah. Have a seat.
Why don't you let me
hook up your fade?
Fade?
Yeah, you know,
edge you up,
clean you up
just a little bit.
You're looking good,
but I can always
make it better.
Huh. Dig that.
What's this all about, hmm?
What do you mean?
You acting like, you know,
I'm Big Willie
or something like that.
You treating me all good.
What's going on?
Well, actually, I, um...
I need a favor.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
AHMAD: When
I first saw Simuel,
I knew he was up to no good.
He wanted Bird bad,
and there wasn't nothing
he wouldn't do or say
to get her.
Yeah, something bad
was about to happen.
It was as plain to see
as all those phat suits
he was always wearing.
(INAUDIBLE)
What do you think?
You know, you got much game,
Bird. Much game.
I learned from you.
(CHUCKLES)
But what's in this for me?
Bird!
Bird, where you at, baby?
I got some great news.
Bird!
(R&B MUSIC PLAYING)
I found a gig.
(LAUGHING)
Yeah. Kenny
called me yesterday,
and told me to ask
about a job
at the biggest in-house
printing company in town.
So I went in cold,
and they didn't even know
who the hell
Kenny Simmons was.
So I knew I had
to kick some game.
Right.
So I told the man,
next to the Goddamn man,
that I was the best man
for the job,
you know what I'm saying?
Yes.
So, finally,
he looks at me...
Hmm.
Stands there, says,
"You're hired."
Right there on the spot.
Like he knew that I knew
that he knew that I knew
that I... was... the man.
Yeah!
That's right, baby.
You are the man.
You're my man.
And with enough hours, baby,
you know what that means?
What?
We gonna get us
our own place, baby.
Oh, yeah?
Mm-hmm.
-(WOOD CRACKS)
-(BOTH SCREAM)
MAN: (OVER PA) James Dawson,
phone call, line two.
James Dawson,
pick up line two.
You have a phone call.
Hey, Lem, I can't believe you
finished that Johnson job.
I didn't expect you
to finish till tomorrow.
Good job.
Thanks.
Thanks a lot, man.
Hey, can you run
a four-and-a-half by nine
Carver?
Yeah, I can work the Carver.
You sure?
Sure.
Good man.
Lem Harris?
Simuel St. James,
chief executive of sales
and marketing.
What's happening?
Yeah, how ya doing?
I've been hearing
a lot of good things
about you, brother.
I mean, especially the way
you've been handling yourself
with those machines
down there.
I'm no stranger
to hard work.
(CHUCKLES) That's good
to know. Cigar?
Oh, nah.
I don't like cigars.
Sorry. You don't mind,
do you?
Uh, like I was
saying, man,
it's always good to,
you know,
have more enthusiastic,
hard-working employees
like yourself.
I mean, especially, you know,
down there in printing.
I mean, I'm no stranger
to hard work myself.
I'm like you.
You see,
I'm from the hood, too.
But, you see, I make
$80,000 a year
because I was always
willing to sacrifice
whatever I had to in order
to get whatever I wanted.
You see, that's why brothers
got to stick together.
You know, pull one another
up in a time of need.
(CLEARS THROAT)
The white man
ain't gonna do it.
And sooner than you think,
it's gonna be
your responsibility
to help another brother,
just like I helped you.
What are you
talking about?
That I pulled some strings
to get you hired.
I mean, what,
you didn't know?
Kenny Simmons
referred me.
Who?
No. I know your wife...
Bird.
Yeah. She told me about
your little felony situation
and asked me to hook
you up with a gig down
in the print department.
Man, me and...
Me and old Cola,
we, uh, we go way back.
Who the fuck is Cola?
Oh, no. (CHUCKLES)
No, that's, uh...
That's just a little
something, you know,
I used to call her
back in the day, you know.
Since she got that body shaped
like a Coca-Cola bottle, huh?
I mean, she used to just...
She used to just make
a brother want to scream.
MAN: Hey, come on!
I'll beat your ass!
Don't fuck with me!
You can forget
about your job,
motherfucker.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
WOMAN: Aah!
(GASPS)
I want to talk to you
for a minute.
What is wrong with you?
Come here.
I want to talk to you.
Why are you fucking
coming in here tripping?
Get in there!
Think I'm not man enough
to find my own fucking job?
I'm sorry.
You fucking that nigga?
No!
What the fuck you have
to do for him, then, huh?
Ain't no man gonna give you
motherfucking thing free!
I didn't do
nothing with him.
I just told him that I was
gonna go to dinner with him
and that is it.
I'm sorry.
Then what the fuck
is this, huh?
It's nothing!
What the fuck is this?
It ain't shit but
a fucking bracelet!
This don't mean nothing.
Baby, I'm sorry.
Don't fucking touch me!
Lem, I love you.
I just did this for us.
Aah!
You stay the fuck
away from me!
Motherfucker!
Lem! Lem!
(SOBBING)
(BANGING ON DOOR)
Bird!
Honey, it's okay, sweetie.
You can talk...
You can talk to us.
HAROME: Bird, you know,
your sister is out here
getting ready to call
somebody, and I don't want
no drama here...
(VOMITING)
Open up, Bird!
Ohh!
AHMAD: So Aunt Teri
was calling in Cousin Blimp
to whoop Uncle Lem's ass,
all 'cause she thought
Lem had beat up Bird.
Big misunderstanding.
This was one of those times
you just knew things were
gonna get a whole lot worse
before they got any better.
That's just how it was when
my aunties tried to fix
each other's messes.
Hey, no guns. You hear me?
WOMAN: Are you okay?
MAN: Hey, Rick,
give me a shot.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Hello. Maxine,
is Kenny there?
This is Rick,
down at the bar.
Your brother-in-law
is down here,
and he's getting wasted.
I didn't know whether
to call Bird or not,
but I think you need to send
somebody down here to get him.
MAN: Hey, Rick, here you go.
AHMAD: There he is...
Cousin Blimp.
He's one of those cousins
you don't get to see much
'cause he always spends
so much time in jail.
Of all the people Aunt Teri
could have called on
to teach Lem a lesson,
I can't believe
she called on Blimp.
Let me get a couple of brews,
and give my boys a couple, too.
RICK: Who's paying
for this, man?
He's paying.
(SCOFFS)
Yeah, right,
motherfucker.
Checkmate, motherfucker!
(LAUGHS)
What the fuck is wrong
with you, punk?
Hit that punk!
I'm gonna blow your
motherfucking brains out!
Should have brought my Gat.
Shut the fuck up!
(SIREN WAILING)
BIRD: Stop the car, Kenny!
Kenny, pull over!
BIRD: Lem!
Lem!
Ahmad, stay in the car!
BIRD: That's my husband!
Wait! That's my husband!
KENNY: Hey, Bird, come on!
No, no! Bird!
BIRD: Wait, officer! Please,
somebody help!
(INDISTINCT SHOUTING)
AHMAD: Kicking Simuel's ass
was one thing,
but being an ex-felon
and having that gun
landed Uncle Lem
right back where
he didn't want to be, jail.
We're talking serious time.
Sure enough, the family
was starting to fall apart.
BIRD: No! Lem!
Hey.
(MUSIC PLAYS SOFTLY)
Teri in?
Uh, she's at the hospital.
Any change?
No.
(CLEARS THROAT)
(MUSIC STOPS)
It's beautiful.
For your CD?
I don't know.
It's a little something
I'm messing around with.
Hey...
Any news on your audition?
(GIGGLES)
Get out of here!
(LAUGHING)
Oh, yeah, I'm pretty
happy about it.
I'm sure you are.
I was so scared.
You?
(GIGGLES)
I gave two weeks
at my firm today.
I quit.
Man, when your CD drops,
you are going to blow up.
Oh, I don't know
about all that.
Let's celebrate.
(LAUGHTER)
MILES: Oh, oh.
Miles...
I'm moving out
this weekend.
Teri and I living
under the same roof together
is not working.
Teri's tough.
So you letting her
run you out of here, huh?
You're damn right.
No. Besides that,
I need my own space.
I'm always on the go,
and I can't stay
in one place too long.
And I got
this new gig, so...
So you gotta go.
I don't know.
It's always been like that.
But, you know,
we're all cool.
There's no hostilities
or anything like that.
It's just...
When it's time to go,
it's time to go.
Ha. That's bullshit.
Excuse me?
Sounds like bullshit.
I mean, that's, uh,
a lonely life.
You should...
Stop pretending
you don't need anybody,
'cause you're just
lying to yourself.
That's how I see it.
I'm going up
to the studio.
(SIGHS)
(MUSIC PLAYS)
(MUSIC STOPS)
(BOTH MOAN)
TERI: You never know.
You never know.
AHMAD: Yeah.
TERI: You have to
just be yourself.
Miles?
AHMAD: Uncle Miles,
we're home.
Well, he must be
upstairs in the studio
on the roof.
Oh, the studio.
Let's go.
(GRUNTING)
Oh, I love it out here,
Aunt Teri.
I know you love it
out here.
Um, we got to go.
But, Aunt Teri, I thought...
Back to your house.
Aunt Teri...
No, let's just
go back, okay?
(BOTH PANTING)
(LAUGHTER IN DISTANCE)
AHMAD: I don't know why
we left Miles and Aunt Teri's
house so fast
or why Aunt Teri
was so upset
all of a sudden.
All I know is she didn't
say a word the whole trip.
We headed back over
to my house that night.
Everybody was getting together
for my mom and dad's
11th year anniversary party.
ALL: Happy anniversary!
(R&B MUSIC PLAYING)
(ALL CHEERING)
♪ Why'd you have to go?
Don't leave me
♪ What about you?
What about me?
♪ What about us?
What we gon' do?
(SIGHS)
(SNIFFLES)
♪ Why'd you have to go?
Don't leave me
♪ What about you?
What about me?
♪ What about us?
What we gon' do?
♪ Total, help me sing
Total, help me sing ♪
(ROMANTIC MUSIC PLAYING)
MAXINE: Mm.
KENNY: Mm.
(KENNY SPEAKING INDISTINCTLY)
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
AHMAD: For a party,
there sure seemed to be
a lot of tension in the air,
especially between
Teri and Miles.
At one point, I think
I even saw Aunt Teri crying.
Not even my mama
could say why.
KENNY: Good God almighty.
At least my folks seemed
to be getting along all right,
which is always cool.
MAXINE: Mm. (CHUCKLING)
Ahem.
Uh, honey, uh,
why don't you get everybody
together in the kitchen
so we can talk, okay?
Mm.
Want to dance?
(CHUCKLING)
Oh.
Whoo!
(TERI SOBBING)
(SNIFFLES)
Teri, you okay?
Are you all right?
Oh, after all these years,
you and Max
are still together.
I still envy that.
(SNIFFLES)
I, uh...
I always thought that
maybe if you and I
had gotten married,
life would be different.
Yeah, but it wouldn't.
I'd find a way
to screw it up.
Teri, you can't...
What y'all doing in here?
Oh, just talking about
this cake. Mm!
It was good.
Yeah, real good.
Um, since
we're all together
here tonight,
I feel that this is
a good time to talk about
Mama's hospital bills.
And y'all know her insurance
ain't gonna cover everything.
KENNY: We're talking
about it since the five
of us are all here.
So maybe we can all pitch in,
take care of this tonight?
Yes.
Well, what about
all that money Mama
has stashed somewhere?
That's just a myth, Bird.
Oh.
So...
I feel that Teri and Miles
could pay for everything,
and then maybe we can
pay you all back
in installments or some...
(SIGHS) Don't you
start running that game
on me again.
What, do you expect me
to bail Lem out of jail, too?
Now, come on, Teri.
Lem doesn't have anything
to do with this, okay?
How we can pay
for Mama's bills is
by selling the big house.
What?
We are not selling
the house.
Mama and Daddy
saved their whole life
for that house, Teri.
We can't even agree
on anything as small
as Sunday dinners.
Nobody's paying for the taxes
or the utilities except me.
And now we can finally
put Uncle Pete in a home
like we've been
talking about for years.
We are not putting
Uncle Pete in a home.
Mama would kill us.
MAXINE: You are tripping.
I'm selling the house.
You're not
selling the house.
I am the guardian
of her estate.
That means
I make the decisions.
Come on, now, Teri,
listen to what they're
saying, all right?
Your mama worked hard
to keep that house
in the family,
for everyone,
for you and your family...
Oh, fuck the family!
The family! I let the family
in my house, you know what?
The family fucked my husband.
(GASPS)
Yeah, Faith fucked my husband.
Miles.
Teri.
What are you gonna say, huh?
MILES: Teri.
"Teri," what?
Can we talk about this?
Can we talk about what?
Fuck you!
Teri, whoa, whoa, whoa!
(HYSTERICAL SCREAMING)
Teri!
Let it go!
WOMAN: Oh, my goodness.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Get out.
I'm so sorry.
Get out!
I never...
Get the fuck out!
Oh, God.
(SOBBING)
BIRD: It's okay.
It's okay, Teri.
It's gonna be okay.
WOMAN: (OVER PA)
Second floor nursing station,
maintenance.
AHMAD: In the five weeks
Big Mama was in that coma,
every grown-up in the family
managed somehow to go crazy.
I know, 'cause I just
about went crazy, too.
You...
(CLEARING THROAT)
You were...
Here...
Weren't you?
Yeah.
Everybody was worried
about you,
but not me.
I knew you'd come around.
I love you, Big Mama.
The family's...
A mess, isn't it?
A lot of bad things happened
while you were gone.
If you let...
Bad things stop you...
You won't be here
for the good things.
I'm tired, baby.
My soul is tired.
I need you to do
something for me.
Only you can do it.
I need you to...
(COUGHING)
Big Mama, what's wrong?
Big Mama.
Son, you're gonna
have to wait outside.
It's okay, son.
We'll take good care
of her for you.
(COUGHING CONTINUES)
Excuse me.
WOMAN: (OVER PA)
Dr. Horowitz, please report
to the nursing station.
Dr. Horowitz
WOMAN: (SINGING)
♪ Why
♪ Should I feel
♪ Discouraged
♪ Why
♪ Should the shadows come
♪ And why
♪ Should my heart
♪ Be lonely
♪ And long
♪ For heaven
♪ And home
♪ When Jesus is
♪ My potion
♪ A constant friend
♪ Is he
♪ His eye
♪ Is on
♪ The sparrow
♪ And I know
♪ He watches me...
AHMAD: Pulling together
in times of need.
That had always been
Big Mama's job,
but who was gonna do it
now that she was gone?
♪ And I know
♪ He watches
♪ Me ♪
Mama ain't even lukewarm
in the ground yet,
and that damn girl
got her house for sale.
Uncle Pete?
What you doing
out of your room?
We going
to the creek today, Joe?
We can catch
some trout for dinner.
Put it in the iron pot,
sear it with lard
or cooking oil, Joe.
No.
I'm Maxine, Uncle Pete.
Joe's daughter.
She's gone.
She's dead.
Remember Daddy
used to raise hogs?
He'd gut 'em,
and he'd cure
the cut-up meat
in brine, and...
And put 'em
in the smokehouse
for sausages.
Mm, mm, mm.
Daddy's gone now.
So you got to take care
of me now, Joe.
That's right.
I'm gonna take
good care of you.
Come on, now,
Uncle Pete.
You want some catfish?
Huh?
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
Look. There she is.
Teri.
Hi.
We didn't order yet,
'cause we were waiting
for you to get here.
(SIREN WAILING)
What's up?
Look, uh, Teri, I know
you're mad at the world
for what's happened
between you and Miles.
I understand.
But you're taking it out
on the whole family,
and that's not right.
Sorry.
We're gonna stop the sale
of Mama's house.
So I went to Kenny's lawyer,
and I drew up a motion
to cease and desist.
Sorry.
Okay.
Okay?
I'm sorry, too.
Well, Teri,
don't leave.
Why doesn't that
surprise me?
I gotta go to the bathroom.
You okay?
Huh?
Lem's gonna be a daddy.
So you're the fish
in Mama's dream.
Yeah.
Wow.
(CHUCKLES)
Maxie, I miss him
so much.
I know, Bird,
but you can't call your ex
to help your husband
find a job behind his back.
A man
has to be a man,
and if he feels
that you take that
away from him,
he has nothing.
Like with Mama.
You remember
when Daddy went
and lost all that money
gambling? Remember?
Yes.
She didn't trip.
She just did
what she had to do,
and she left him
with his dignity.
You see
what I'm saying?
Men need that.
Yeah.
I guess you're right.
(SINGING)
♪ I'm gonna be
an auntie ♪
Oh, God.
I just wish
I could be like you.
Please.
And so does Teri.
That's why she acts
the way she does.
Girl, you got
your own shop,
and Teri's got
a great job at the firm.
Shoot, all I got
is a husband
and some kids,
but they badasses.
(CHUCKLES)
Mama always said that
you were the strongest one
in the family.
I just want to say thank you
for always supporting me.
You're my sister, girl.
(LAUGHING)
I love you, Maxie.
I love you, too.
Come here, girl.
It's gonna be
all right.
Yeah.
Just fine.
Now we gotta get
some bottles, Pampers.
You ready for that?
Oh, God. Yeah, I guess.
(CHUCKLES) Get ready.
Yeah, it's Teri Joseph
for Jonathan Oliver, please.
AHMAD: Teri must have
felt really bad about
what she did to Lem,
'cause the next thing
you knew,
she was calling in a favor
from some downtown big shot.
Um, I have a favor.
MAXINE: And the last steal.
The way you just pulled up
and scored.
AHMAD: Mom.
Sweet move, baby,
sweet move.
Yeah, but, Mama,
why you always
gotta be so loud?
(CHUCKLES) Hey,
I don't care
what they say.
You my baby,
and I'm proud of you.
Mama, think you can
hook up a victory dinner?
Sure, baby,
anything you want.
Think I could grub
on some lima beans,
neck bones, greens
with some hot sauce,
hot cakes,
and some fried chicken.
Dang. All of that?
All of that.
All right.
Besides, I haven't cooked
like that since...
So when you want to have
this little victory dinner?
Sunday...
At Big Mama's.
You're up to something.
Huh?
(IMITATING) Huh?
Boy, I carried you
for nine months,
went through
23 hours, 45 minutes...
...10 seconds of labor.
Wiped your little butt
while your little
ding-a-ling
pee-peed in my face.
So Mama knows when
you up to something.
You're trying to get everybody
together for Sunday dinner,
aren't you?
Big Mama wants me to.
I think that's what
she was trying to tell me
before she died.
You liked
that last shot, right?
Oh, man, that last shot
was the bomb.
Flow, you know.
Just keep doing
like that, baby,
and when you get older
you're gonna be able
to get a fat contract, right?
Buy a house. You're gonna
get me a Lexus, all right?
Lexus, right.
And a fur. You know
what I'm saying?
Brother be like...
Guys, that sounded good,
but I'm still missing a note.
Come on.
Let's do it again.
MILES: Let's try it
again, all right?
Here we go, here we go.
One, two,
three, four.
♪ Girl
♪ I care about you
♪ I'm there for you
♪ So why don't you care
♪ For me?
♪ Like I care about you ♪
Good, good, better.
Yeah. Let's take
a break, all right?
Right. Leave the little man
to his business.
I'm glad you could
make it down, shorty.
I'm glad
I could, too.
It's been tough, you know?
With school and working
at the shop afterwards.
I'm trying to coordinate
what to do
with all that loot
Big Mama left me.
What loot?
Dead presidents?
Cash?
When did she leave it to you?
The day she died.
See, I was the only one
at the hospital.
And Big Mama told me where
she stashed a lot of money
none of you all knew about.
So how much money
are you talking about?
Lots. I mean beaucoup.
Beaucoup?
Beaucoup.
See, Faith,
I was thinking.
Maybe you could help me figure
out what to do with the dough.
Now, this is not
the money from the will?
Aunt Teri, you're the
smartest in the family.
You know that's right.
If I was your son...
Mm-hmm?
Would you invest
in my future?
Sure.
Do the right thing
for family?
Absolutely.
See, I figure
if you help me,
I can give you a third.
You know, like a fee.
A fee?
Yeah, a fee.
Then you could pay off
Big Mama's bills.
So you won't
have to sell the house.
And I can give you
a percentage
if you help me invest it.
Then maybe you can
use the money
to promote your new CD.
Have you told anybody
else about this?
No, but I'd be willing
to give you some of it.
Then you could
pay off Aunt Teri's loan.
Why don't you tell me...
Where the money is?
So let's go get it.
When would be a good time?
Sunday at 3:00,
at Big Mama's.
(KNIFE CHOPPING)
Hey.
AHMAD: Hey.
What y'all
doing here?
Oh, just, uh, cooking
a little Sunday dinner.
All right. Get on out the way
and let the ladies handle this.
Okay, after all
the hard work is done,
you're gonna come in.
You can go work hard
with that remote control
and watch some football,
all right?
I can do that.
Yeah, you can. Mm-hmm.
You sure?
You don't need anything?
No, thank you.
KENNY: Mm-hmm.
You want me to start
these dumplings?
Yeah, but you watch
that measuring,
'cause you know how you are.
(WHISPERING)
I'm gonna kick your butt.
Why didn't you tell me?
AHMAD: Well,
this would be the test,
to see if 40 years
of tradition
and a heap of Mama's soul food
could pull our family
right back together again.
(FOOTBALL GAME ON TELEVISION)
Hey, Aunt Teri,
what's up?
Hey.
Mm.
There's a car outside.
Is your mom here?
Somebody cooking?
Why don't you go
in the kitchen and see?
(SNIFFING)
AHMAD: Yeah.
Smells in the kitchen
bringing back
the good old days.
Mm, dumplings,
deep-fried catfish,
macaroni and cheese,
and sweet corn bread.
The kind Big Mama used to
make look like pound cake
so us kids would eat it.
I just wanted the good
old feelings back, too...
And so did Big Mama.
Hey, Miles,
what's up, man?
How you doing?
What's going on
here, Ahmad?
Uh, we having
Sunday dinner, man.
We got some
string beans, catfish,
chicken and dumplings, man,
some corn bread.
I don't think
I should be here.
(DOOR OPENS)
What's happening, man?
Hey, Lem, when did you
get out of jail?
What's going on?
Hey, uh...
MAXINE: How you
doing, Miles?
Why don't you come on in
and have a seat?
We're going to serve dinner
in a minute.
What's going on in there?
We're having
Sunday dinner.
Sunday dinner?
(SIGHS)
I fucked up, huh?
How's Bird doing?
She's in there.
Why don't you
go ask her?
It looks
like a family thing
going on in there.
I don't want to butt in.
Why not?
You're family.
Hey, Ahmad, um...
I know I let you down,
and, I'm sorry.
But I want you to know,
I ain't beat on your Auntie.
I pushed her,
and that was bad enough,
but I didn't hit her.
I would never,
ever hit a woman.
Do you believe me?
Ahmad, your mama
said get upstairs
and wash your hands
and get ready for dinner.
I'll leave
you two alone.
You're home?
Oh, baby.
I missed you so much.
I missed you.
Are you okay?
I'm fine, baby.
I messed up, baby.
I messed up.
I'm sorry.
I love you.
I love you, too.
I have something
to tell you.
Oh, yeah?
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
Ahmad? Ahmad?
I can't even
believe she's here.
(SIGHS)
Come on.
Hey.
AHMAD: Hey, Faith,
what's up?
Ahmad, what's going on?
How come everybody's here?
We just having
Sunday dinner.
Sunday dinner?
Yeah, Sunday dinner.
You know, we got some
chicken and dumplings,
some string beans,
catfish, some...
Not cool, Ahmad.
I'm out of here.
Faith!
Wait. Please, stay.
Please?
AHMAD: Dear Lord,
thank you for allowing us
another day on Earth,
another day
to glorify your name
and sanctify ourselves
with your mercy.
Lord, I'm grateful
that the people I love
most in the world
are here to celebrate life
and the lessons as it unfolds.
And let one of those lessons
be acceptance and love,
so we can be a family again
and love each other
like we used to.
In Christ Jesus' name, amen.
Amen.
MAXINE: Amen.
REVEREND WILLIAMS: Amen.
Mm-mm-mm.
It's so good to be back here.
I missed this place.
I've got my favorite food.
You can't find this food
anyplace...
Well, I have a surprise
for everyone later,
but for now,
why don't we just eat?
I say amen to that.
ALL: Amen.
(LAUGHTER)
LEM: Everybody, um...
I got my job back.
BIRD: Oh,
that's good, Lem.
Congratulations.
BIRD: That's great.
Yeah, they asked
a brother back to work,
because they know
I'm a good, strong,
skilled worker.
That's right.
So, how'd you get
out of jail, Lem?
To tell you the truth, man,
I don't even know.
Somebody talked
to somebody,
and the charges
got dropped.
Here I am.
Well, we glad to
have you home, brother.
Yes, sir.
That's right.
My boo is home.
Actually, I called a friend
of mine at the D.A.'s office
for a favor.
I felt bad.
Well, you should
feel bad.
Because of you,
I had to spend
weeks in jail.
You should be thankful.
Now you can spend
some time and take care
of your pregnant wife.
BIRD: You know what, Teri?
You need to mind your own
damn business, all right?
Didn't nobody
ask you for your help.
You need to be worrying
about your husband
and why
he's sleeping with her.
Gee.
No, sit.
No, let her go
if she wants to.
Teri, I'm sorry,
but she's always
running away.
You're family,
and we're going
to deal with this.
Baby, go get me some more peas
and take your sister with you.
BIRD: Always worrying about
somebody else's business.
You need to take care
of your own husband.
So, was that it, Miles?
I didn't take care of you?
You know,
we haven't been happy
for a long time now.
We used to have
so much fun.
I don't know what happened.
It seems that
everything I love...
I lose.
Well... Um...
(CLEARS THROAT)
Good luck with
Mother Joe's money.
M-mother Joe's money?
Yeah, what money?
What are you talking about?
Supposedly, Mama has some
large amount of money
stashed someplace
in the house
that she was saving
for Ahmad, and...
That's why
we're all here tonight.
Ahmad?
Get in here.
KENNY: Ahmad.
MAXINE: Right now.
Ahmad, where's this money
that Mother Joe supposedly
left you?
There isn't any money.
I made it all up.
MAXINE: You made it up?
Ahmad, what have I
told you about lying?
You know
better than that.
It's not my fault!
It's y'all's fault!
Y'all messed up the family!
Can't you see that?
(AHMAD CRYING)
Big Mama wanted me
to get everyone together
for a Sunday dinner.
But I didn't know
how to do that,
because all
y'all do is fight.
So I lied...
Lied about the money
so you'd come.
So we could be a family again.
Y'all know that's
what Big Mama wanted.
Baby...
Come here.
It's okay.
You guys smell that?
Smell what?
Smells like it's coming
from the kitchen.
You didn't mess
with the stove,
did you?
I'll go look.
Whoa!
Oh, shit! Come on!
Uhh! Uhh!
LEM: Let me get some water!
Aah!
Get back! Get back!
BIRD: Oh, my God!
Look out! Look out!
Oh! Oh, whoa! Whoa! Look out!
KENNY: It's coming from
the back of the stove!
Come on!
It ain't going to work!
It ain't working!
Oh, my God!
Uhh!
The house!
Wait!
LEM: It's getting out of hand!
KENNY: We need
an extinguisher!
Look for an extinguisher!
Yeah!
(COUGHING)
No.
BIRD: Oh, my God.
Oh, my goodness.
Oh, no.
What happened?
I don't know.
I...
MILES: Ohh.
I forgot.
I left the towel on the stove.
MAXINE: Oh, Ahmad...
(DOOR BANGS OPEN)
(ALL SCREAMING)
Uncle Pete,
are you all right?
Ooh. Just got a little
on your face.
He didn't mean nothing.
This is, uh, my surprise,
everybody.
Uncle Pete.
Uncle Pete?
(LAUGHTER)
I'm... I'm sorry, man.
AHMAD: Look at this.
(CONFUSED CLAMOR)
Ho ho!
Look at all
this money!
(EXCITED SHOUTING)
AHMAD: Big Mama
really did have a pile
of money hidden away,
and she had it stashed
in the last place
we'd all think to look...
Uncle Pete's TV.
(ALL CHEERING)
Now I understand what
soul food was all about.
See, during slavery,
us Black folks didn't have
a whole lot to celebrate,
so cooking became the way
we expressed our love
for one another.
And that's what those
Sunday dinners meant to us.
More than just eating,
it was a time for sharing
our joys and sorrows,
something the old folks
say is missing
in today's families.
Things got better
for my family after that.
And even though Miles
and Aunt Teri broke up,
it hasn't stopped Miles
from coming around
every now and then
and filling his belly
with Mama's soul food.
Lem and Bird
are doing good, too.
They got their own place,
and they're expecting
that baby any day now.
My mama and Aunt Teri
are cool again,
at least for the time being.
And Faith is finally
a part of the family, too.
And as you can see,
we didn't sell the big house.
No way, no how.
And even though we all miss
Big Mama's cooking,
laughter, and love,
none of us feel like
life cheated her none.
See, she accomplished
all the things
she set out to do,
to build a strong family,
with a rich tradition,
and to leave love
in her footprints.
Thanks... Big Mama.
♪ You taught me everything
♪ And everything
you've given me
♪ I'll always keep it inside
♪ And you're
the driving force in my life
♪ Yeah-eah-eah
♪ There isn't anything
or anyone that I could be
♪ And it just
wouldn't feel right
♪ If I didn't have you
by my side
♪ Oh
♪ You were there for me
♪ To love and care for me
♪ When skies were gray
♪ Whenever I was down
♪ You were always there
♪ To comfort me
♪ And no one else can be
what you have been to me
♪ You will always be
♪ The girl in my life
♪ For all times
♪ Mama, Mama
♪ You know I love you
♪ Mama
♪ Ooh
You're the queen of my heart
♪ You are
♪ Your love is like
Tears from the stars
♪ Mama
I just want you to know
♪ Lovin' you
is like food to my soul
♪ Bum-bum
♪ Oh
♪ Yeah, yeah
♪ You are the food
♪ To my soul
♪ Yes, you are ♪
♪ Uhh, uhh, uhh, uhh
♪ Don't you stop it
♪ Don't you stop
what you're doin'
♪ Oh
♪ You don't really
want to stop
♪ No, you don't
♪ Don't you stop it
♪ Don't you stop
what you're doin'
♪ Yeah, yeah
♪ You don't really
want to stop
♪ Check it out, yeah, come on
♪ Whether you like it hard
over live guitars
♪ Anything dropped
If it's hot, it's ours
♪ If it's not, it's yours
We on the job
♪ Everybody eatin'
♪ Everybody involved
♪ You can't stop that
like you can't stop rap
♪ Bad boy, stop
What's the chance of that?
♪ We don't stop
♪ So check the mansions
and stacks
♪ And we don't have
to answer to jack
♪ No wonder
we had this rap shit locked
♪ For eight straight summers
♪ Pull up at the party
♪ Eight straight Hummers
♪ Six be the sixth
Seventh and eighth wonders
♪ Pop corks
We be the toast of New York
♪ And out west
We want y'all to understand
♪ All we wanna do
is make you dance
♪ We know the song
ain't done wrong
♪ When the party is hot
♪ Y'all don't really want us
to stop, do you?
♪ Don't you stop it
♪ Don't you stop
what you're doin'
♪ Oh
♪ You don't really
want to stop
♪ Nah
♪ Don't you stop it
♪ Don't you stop
what you're doin'
♪ You don't really
want to stop
♪ You can pump this
in your Jeep on an off-road
♪ Pump this through your Bose
on the way to the tow
♪ Bang this till you're
bein' old when you at home
♪ Or on the six-four
sittin' on chrome
♪ Yo, we don't stall
We ball while you
playin' the wall
♪ We in the middle
of the dance floor gettin' off
♪ We got a bunch of hot chicks
♪ Gettin' live with us
♪ At the end of the night
They gonna slide with us
♪ Don't you stop it
♪ Don't you stop
what you're doin'
♪ You don't really
want to stop
♪ No, baby, uh-uh
♪ Don't you stop it
♪ Don't you stop
what you're doin'
♪ You don't really
want to stop ♪